Finding Aid for Board for Student Publications (University of Michigan) records, 1903-1998
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Board for Student Publications (University of Michigan) records 1903-1998 1930-1990
University of Michigan. Board for Student Publications.
8719 Bimu F3 2
The Board for Student Publications was founded in 1903, as the Board in Control of the Michigan Daily, with the authority over all operation s of the Michigan Daily, including content and editorial issues. Its authority was extended to all student publications in 1908, and its name changed to The Board in Control of Student Publications. In 1969, the Board name was changed to the Board for Student Publications. It retained financial control over student publications, but only serves in an advisory capacity on editorial issues. The records mostly consist of the Board’s minutes, and also include correspondence of board chairmen, materials pertaining to various student publications, financial materials, and blueprints and drawings of the Student Publications Building during its various renovations.
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group came to the library in several accessions. The Board in Control of Student Publications (Donor No. 1509 ) donated four volumes of minutes in 1953, and additional records were donated in 1998, 2002 and 2006.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Board for Student Publications, initially entitled the Board in Control of the Michigan Daily, was established June 2, 1903, by the University of Michigan Senate. The Senate adopted the recommendation proposed by Professor Volney M. Spaulding, who reported on behalf of a special committee on non-athletic student organizations, that a board be established to regulate the Michigan Daily, the student newspaper. The Board was to be an agent of the Board of Regents. It was authorized to acquire the stock and property of the paper and was given full control of all questions pertaining to the paper, subject to Senate regulations. The Board consisted of seven members, four from the Senate and three from the student body. The four Senate members of the first board were Fred N. Scott, chair, Allen S. Whitney, Alfred H. Lloyd, and Frank L. Sage.
On November 24, 1908, the University Senate changed the name of the Board to the Board in Control of Student Publications. Its jurisdiction extended to cover all periodical publications edited by members of the University of Michigan student body (with the exception of the Michiganensian for the school year 1908-1909). The Board was incorporated as a non-profit corporation in 1919. In 1922, the Board appointed a committee to consider plans for a new publications building. The plans were approved in 1930. The new building, the Student Publications Building, contained office space for all the student publications but only had facilities to print the Michigan Daily, as it was felt that the printing of the other publications could be done more efficiently through contracts with commercial printers.
A committee on university publications of the Alumni Advisory Council held a meeting in May 1932 at which it was pointed out that the Michigan Daily was regarded by many as an official organ of the university. The committee advocated somewhat stricter control of the material printed in the paper. As a result, two alumni actively engaged in newspaper work were added to the board in 1933: Lee A. White of the Detroit News and Stuart Perry of the Adrian Daily Telegram.
At that time the Board took over the management of the various publications that were owned and operated by students. A policy of allowing the managing editors and business managers a percentage of the net profits of the publication for each year was eventually replaced by a system of salaries. Each year the Board appointed the senior staff of the various student publications for the ensuing academic year. In doing so, members of the Board considered experience on the publication staff, college grades, and views of the candidates regarding the challenges involved with the position. In recent years, responsibility for choosing senior staff has been placed entirely in the hands of students.
In 1969, the authority of the Board, and the name, were changed. In 1992 the Board formed a Co-chair position to assist the Board Chair. The Board is now called the Board for Student Publications. It continues to retain overall financial responsibility for the publications, but now only serves in an advisory capacity on editorial questions. In 1992 the Board changed their organization, and decided to have a chair and a co-chair.
Chairs of the Board
1903-1927 Fred N. Scott
1927-1929 Morris P. Tilley
1929-1932 Robert C. Angell
1932-1937 Louis A. Strauss
1937-1941 William A. McLaughlin
1941-1945 Gail E. Densmore
1945-1951 Paul G. Kauper
1951-1952 Lionel Laing
1952-1959 John W. Reed
1959-1962 Olin L. Browder
1962-1972 Luke K. Cooperrider
1969-1972 L. Hart Wright
1972-1978 Lawrence Berlin
1978-1981 Thomas M. Sawyer
1981-1984 George D. Cameron III
1985-1987 Charles R. Eisendrath
1987-1991 Amnon Rosenthal
1991-1998 Leon Jaroff
1998-2000 Mark Haas
2000-2003 Jane Myers
2003-2004 Barbara McQuade
2004-2005 Kim Clarke
Co-Chairs of the Board
1991-1992 Tom Croxton
1993-1995 Gayl D. Ness
1993-1998 Joan Lowenstein
1998-1999 Bill Nauser
1999-2001 Andy Gottesman
2001-2005 Alan Lenhof
For a lengthier history of the board through 1958, see The University of Michigan An Encyclopedic Survey, Volume IV, pp. 1904-1906.
The records of the Board for Student Publications, 1903-1990 are divided into two series: Minutes and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Michigan daily.; University of Michigan. Board for Student Publications.; University of Michigan. Board in Control of Student Publications.; University of Michigan--Periodicals.; University of Michigan--Students--Periodicals.; Student Publications Building (University of Michigan)
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Board in Control of Student Publications.
- Minutes 1903-1990 (Box 1)
  The Minutes series (1903-1990, 3.0 linear feet) contains the minutes of each Board meeting, including meeting agendas and proceedings, as well as supplementary financial reports, correspondence, and attachments discussed during the meetings. Minutes from 1903 to 1945 are bound into four volumes. The remainder of the minutes are foldered by individual meeting. All minutes are arranged chronologically. There are no minutes for the years 1946-1949, and only minutes for one meeting in 1970.
  - November 19, 1903-May 29, 1915, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - November 5, 1921-May 29, 1936, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - December 16, 1936-May 20, 1940, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - October 16, 1940-June 11, 1945, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - August 21, 1945-May 18, 1949, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - October 3, 1949-May 10, 1952, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - October 17, 1952-May 21, 1954, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - October 1, 1954-May 17, 1955, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - October 4, 1955-May 16, 1956, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - October 9, 1956-May 8, 1957, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - October 11, 1957-May 21, 1958, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - October 3, 1958-May 19, 1960, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - October 5, 1960-May 14, 1963, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - October 1, 1963-April 26, 1965, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - September 13, 1965-May 25, 1967, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - October 16, 1967-May 24, 1971, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - September 22, 1971-September 29, 1975, 15 folders (Box 2)
  - February 5, 1976-October 15, 1979, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - February 6, 1980-April 12, 1984, 20 folders (Box 3)
  - January 30, 1985-March 21, 1990 undated, 33 folders (Box 3)
  - April 18, 1990-April 10, 1991, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - November 11 1991-April, 1992, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - September 28, 1992-April 27, 1993, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - September 21, 1993-April 20, 1994, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - September 26, 1994-April 17, 1995, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - September 18, 1995-April 22, 1996, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - September 27, 1996-April 14, 1997, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - September 22, 1997-April 27, 1998, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - 1998 (Box 3)
  - 1999 (Box 3)
- Topical Files 1903-1985
  The Topical Files series (1903-1985, 2 linear feet) consists mostly of correspondence, as well as reports, clippings, and other materials. The series is organized into two subseries,1903-1982 (1.75 linear feet) and 1924-1985 (0.25 linear feet),reflecting two different accessions of material form the board. The material within the series reflects the role of the board in arranging and sanctioning printing and photographic contracts, acting as liaison between the students and the university administration (especially concerning controversial actions on the part of editors), and appointing staff positions. There are three main sections within the series. Correspondence (1931-1978) is the correspondence of the chairmen of the board, often pertaining to issues about the content and reporting of the student publications. Publications (1903-1980) contains materials related to the operation, finances, and content of specific student publications. The majority of materials are about the Michigan Daily and the Michiganensian. The Student Publications Building Construction and Renovation Plans (1930-1980) are mostly blueprints and building plans for the initial construction, and subsequent renovations, of the Student Publications Building.
  The Senior Staff Applications, 1952-1957, which are part of the Topical Files series, are arranged chronologically and consist of student applications for senior staff positions on the various University of Michigan student publications. Approximately five folders worth of applications have been reduced to one "sample" folder, to represent the variety of student applicants, including men and women of varying levels of experience. The applications are primarily for positions with the Gargoyle, the Generation, and the Michigan Daily.
  Also of note are the surveys about the publications and their readership. Two were conducted about the Michigan Daily, in 1959 and 1972. The "Publication Questionnaires, 1954-1956" contains detailed answers to requests for information about the functioning of the Board.
  The Topical Files series (1924-1985, 0.3 linear feet) consists of correspondence, reports, clippings, and other materials. Of research interest are the Vietnam War and Watergate clippings, and the handicap barrier issue arising in 1980.
  - 1903-1982
    - Alumni Association 1951 (Box 4)
    - Articles of Incorporation (copies) 1919-1951 (Box 4)
    - Associated Press 1969 (Box 4)
    - Board Membership 1935-1961, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Board Problems 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Bogdonoff Award 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    - Bylaws and Rules 1915-1967 (Box 4)
    - College Press Service 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Committee on University Publications 1932 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - 1931-1951 (Box 4)
      - 1952-1962, 7 folders (Box 4)
      - 1936-1965 (Box 4)
      - 1966-1978, 8 folders (Box 4)
      - Laing, Lionel 1951 (Box 4)
      - McLaughlin, William 1937-1940 (Box 4)
      - Regents of the University of Michigan 1972-1973 (Box 4)
      - White, Ink 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - Financial Materials
      - Accounts Receivable 1950-1951 (Box 4)
      - Annual Reports 1931-1961 (Box 4)
      - Audit Reports Correspondence 1947-1953, 1989 (Box 4)
      - Budget 1982-1983 (Box 4)
      - Transactions with the University of Michigan 1950-1952 (Box 4)
    - Plant Conversion Committee 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Publication Questionnaire Correspondence 1954-1956 (Box 4)
    - Publications
      - Gargoyle, 1937-1951 (Box 4)
      - Generation, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
      - Michigan Daily
        - Censorship (Fred Warner Neil case) 1937 (Box 4)
        - Correspondence 1936-1954, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - History 1903-1963 (Box 4)
        - Libel Suit (Douglas Harvey) 1975 (Box 4)
        - The Michigan Daily Stylebook, 1968 (Box 4)
        - Michigan Free Press Insert (refusing to distribute), 1975 (Box 4)
        - Income and Expense 1936-1951 (Box 5)
        - Policies and Staff Organization (Box 5)
        - Quality of Reporting, Concerns 1935-1967 (Box 5)
        - Rate and Publication Schedules 1960-1980 (Box 5)
        - Readership Survey 1964 (Box 5)
        - Survey of Advertising 1959 (Box 5)
        - Survey of the Michigan Daily 1972, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Survey of other schools' abortion ad policies 1971 (Box 5)
        - Survey of other schools' publications 1960s (Box 5)
        - 60th Anniversary Reunion-Guest Book 1950 (Box 5)
      - Michiganensian
        - Correspondence 1947-1954 (Box 5)
        - Levett Studios (Photographers) 1950 (Box 5)
        - Rogers Printing Company 1950-1955 (Box 5)
        - S.K. Smith Company (Printer) 1947-1954 (Box 5)
        - Staff Organization (Box 5)
      - Michigan Student News, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
      - Panorama 1937 (Box 5)
      - Student Directory 1949-1952, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Record Retention Schedule 1953 (Box 5)
    - Regulations re: Appointment of Student Editors undated (Box 5)
    - Reports to the University of Michigan Senate 1903-1956, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Senior Staff Applications 1952-1957 (Box 5)
    - Service Contracts 1948-1954 (Box 5)
    - Statements and Petitions 1935-1955 (Box 5)
    - Student Publications Building Construction Plans 1930-1932 (Box 5)
    - Student Publications Building Renovation Plans 1943-1980, undated, 8 folders (Box 5)
    - Student Publications Equipment Inventory 1952 (Box 5)
    - University Council 1933-1940 (Box 5)
  - 1924-1985
    - Audit of 1980, 1980-1982 (Box 6)
    - Building Procurement History 1924, 1927, 1931, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    - Handicap Barrier Issue 1980-1981 (Box 6)
    - Publications
      - Michigan Daily
        - "The Daily" Dozen 1942 (Box 6)
        - Financial Crisis at The Daily 1985 (Box 6)
        - Readership Survey 1981 (Box 6)
    - Vietnam War Clippings 1959-1975, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Watergate Clippings 1972 (Box 6)
- Photographs, 1920-1988
  The Photographs series (circa 1920-1988, 0.4 linear feet) contains photographs, film negatives and glass negatives of images possibly used in publications. The photographs of football games, field hockey, and student life from around 1920 are the highlights of this series. Also included are photographs of prominent people visiting the area and photograph series chronicling the arts and Hinduism. The photos are indexed by topic and the personal photographs are alphabetized by name. Where multiple photos occur of a single individual, a separate folder was created to chronicle the individual. The presence of negatives is also noted within the finding aid.
  - Arts Series, circa 1960-1980 (Box 6)
  - Buildings, circa 1920 (Box 6)
    (contains negatives)
  - [Camp Filibert Roth?], circa 1920 (Box 6)
    (contains glass negatives)
  - Football, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Hinduism Series undated (Box 6)
  - Marching Band, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Parades, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - People
    - A-Z, circa 1960-1980, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Fraser, Douglas 1982 (Box 6)
    - Josephson, Paul 1985-1986 (Box 6)
    - Kelly, Leo 1981 (Box 6)
    - Levin, Carl 1978-1986 (Box 6)
    - McGovern, George undated (Box 6)
    - Pierce, Ed 1986 (Box 6)
    - Pursel, Carl undated (Box 6)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor 1957 (Box 6)
    - Shapiro, Harold 1986-1987, undated (Box 6)
    - Tutu, Bishop Desmond 1988 (Box 6)
    - Unknown, circa 1920 (Box 6)
    - Unknown, circa 1960-1980 (Box 6)
  - [Staff Photos?], circa 1980 (Box 6)
  - Stick Wrestling, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Student Life, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Students Drinking, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Swimmers, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Tug of War Rope, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Women's Archery, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Women's Field Hockey, circa 1920 (Box 6)
  - Women's Golf, circa 1920 (Box 6)
Related Material
Related collections at the Bentley Historical Library include:
The Edson Read Sunderland Papers
The Harlan Henthorne Hatcher Papers
Michigan Daily Records
Karl Zeisler Papers